A Guide to the Letters to Ann Eliza Eddy, 1857-1881
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Letters to Ann Eliza Eddy, 1857-1881
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-063
0.2 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection is comprised of letters to Ann Eliza Eddy, living in Troy, New York, dating from 1857-1865. Eddy received letters from Union soldiers, cousins, and friends over the course of the Civil War. There are several photographs of the house and writers included in the collection.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Letters to Ann Eliza Eddy were purchased by Special Collections in 1990.
Arrangement
The letters in the collection are organized alphabetically according to the author's first name.
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of letters to Ann Eliza Eddy, living in Troy, New York, dating from 1857-1865. Eddy received letters from Union soldiers, cousins, and friends over the course of the Civil War. There are several photographs of the house and writers included in the collection.
Both 'Tom,' Eustace McArdle, and 'Worth' are cousins to Ann Eliza Eddy, also nicknamed 'Yi' in several letters from close friends and relatives. Worth was Writing from the 9th regiment of the New York State Militia. Worth wrote primarily about his experience in the army and the battles. McArdle writes from the 22nd, Company A, New York State Militia. Similar to Worth, he sends his best wishes and describes he experience in the army. Tom speaks mostly to Eddy of family business. He describes himself as a 'school boy' and he seems to work in a Naval Office. In a later letter he briefly mentions Japanese ambassadors visiting New York.
In addition to family letters, Ann Eliza Eddy received letters from four more Union Soldiers and one Chief Surgeon, Captain James W. Colville and Lieutenant Walter Knox from the 3rd division of the 2nd Corps of the Army of the Potomac. Colville's letter primarily mentions the war and other hardships. Knox writes about the war and his experience as well, occasionally reminiscing about time he spent in Troy with Eddy.
W.F. Hutchinson writes to Eddy from the 22nd New York Volunteer Infantry. Hutchinson shares details from the war. He reports that a surgeon, Dr. Atherley, died in his November 16th, 1862 letter. Henry Lyster writes to Eddy from the 3rd Brigade of the 2nd Corps. He is the Chief Surgeon with the unit. Henry describes to her the work he does in his letter.
George W. Waldron writes from the 5th Michigan Volunteer Infantry. Waldron seems to be very well educated. Waldron's letters are very descriptive of scenery and weather. He also make allusions to books and musicals including Les Miserables. Waldron reminisces over his time in Troy. Waldron also talks candidly about the wounded: "I always think when any one is wounded that someone is just as bad or worse wounded at home, for a wound of the feelings and of the heart, made by the loss of friends, is frequently more serious and more painful and mortal than a wound of the body. Our 47 000 widows have already applied to the army for pensions during this war. How terrible and numerous have been the wounds received in the army and among homes. How often will the mother in the depth of her anguish doubt the melancholy tale, and how will the little sister unacquainted with death, still expect her brothers to return. Spring will return with it's budding promises, summer with its purpling fruits, and the autumn with its golden harvests, but those who have fallen for their country will come not again, for there is no returning pathway through the tomb."
The other letters Eddy receives are from Sarah R.F. Grebel and 'Helen'. Helen writes to Eddy from Chicago mostly mentioning men she's met, the effects of the war, and the astounding number of widows that she knows. Sarah R.F. Grebel is a widow. In her letter, she describes the loss of her husband who she saw as a close partner and companion.
Biographical Note
All of the letters were written to Ann Eliza Eddy, who lived in Troy New York. She was born 21 August 1807 and died 11 December 1887. According to Ancestry.com records she married Titus Eddy.
Sources:
"New York: State Census 1855."Ancestry Library Edition. Website.
"Find a Grave." Website. http://www.findagrave.com
Index Terms
Persons:
Colville, James W., Captain; Eddy, Ann Eliza; Grebel, Sarah R.F.; Hutchinson, W. F.; Knox, Walter; Lyster, Henery; McArdle, Eustace; Waldron, George W.
Subjects:
Civil War; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Women--History
Genre and Form Terms:
Correspondence
Contents List
- Eustace McArdle, 1861-1862 (Box-folder 1-1)
- George W. Waldron, 1863-1864 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Helen, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Henry Lyster, 1863 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Captain James W. Collvile, 1864 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Sarah R. F. Grebel, 1861 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Tom [Unknown Last Name], 1867 (Box-folder 1-7)
- Walter Knox, 1863-1864 (Box-folder 1-8)
- W. F. Hutchinson, 1861-1862 (Box-folder 1-9)
- Worth, 1862 (Box-folder 1-10)
- Photographs, 1861-1865 (Box-folder 1-11)
- General Grant Letter, 1881 (Box-folder 1-12)